{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This battle was referred to by the Benedictine chronicler Orderic Vitalis as \"Senlac,\" though it may have taken place near Caldbec and Telham Hill. Amatus of Montecassino described how one ruler was killed by an arrow to the eye at this battle, the site of which is marked by Battle Abbey. Weeks before this battle, the losers were forced to engage a Norwegian attack at Fulford and Stamford Bridge. Harold Godwinson was killed in, for ten points, what 1066 victory for William the Conqueror?",
      "answer": "Battle of Hastings"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city's royal namesake was depicted by Charles Henry Niehaus [[NEE-haus]] in an equestrian statue known as the Apotheosis of [this city]. This city hosted a 1904 World's Fair, during which Brookings Hall was constructed for this city's Washington University. Native brewer Ellis Wainwright names a red skyscraper in this city designed by Louis Sullivan. This city is commemorated as the origin of the Lewis and Clark Expedition with the Gateway Arch. For ten points, name this Missouri city located along the Mississippi River.",
      "answer": "St. Louis"
    },
    {
      "question": "U.S. officials opened a warrant for this man's arrest after he traveled to Yugoslavia for a competition in 1992. At age thirteen, this man beat Donald Byrne in the so-called \"Game of the Century.\" This man became World Champion in 1972 by defeating Boris Spassky in Reykjavík and later became a citizen of Iceland. This man refused to defend his title against Anatoly Karpov in 1975 over a rules disagreement. For ten points, name this reclusive American chess Grandmaster.",
      "answer": "Robert \"Bobby\" Fischer"
    },
    {
      "question": "The subject of this event walked a route known as the Via Dolorosa, before meeting his end. During this event, a man named Dismas told its main subject to \"remember me when you come into your kingdom.\" After this event, a soldier named Longinus [[lon-JAI- nus]] pierced the side of this event's central subject, causing water and blood to gush from the wound. For ten points, name this event ordered by Pontius Pilate, in which the Son of God was hung on a cross outside of Jerusalem.",
      "answer": [
        "Crucifixion of Jesus Christ",
        "descriptive answers of the death",
        "killing of Jesus Christ 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the leadup to this event, Alexander Manly refuted Rebecca Felton's op-ed advocating for lynching \"a thousand times a week.\" During this event, a mob protested the election of a mayor representing the Fusionists. Alfred Waddell threatened to \"choke the Cape Fear River with carcasses\" during this event, which included the torching of the Black- owned Daily Record office. William McKinley refused to provide federal assistance to stop, for ten points, what 1898 white supremacist incident in North Carolina?",
      "answer": [
        "Wilmington Insurrection of 1898",
        "Wilmington race riot, Wilmington massacre,",
        "Wilmington Coup"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Russia imposed sanctions on this man and Christopher Wray in April 2021. From 2013 to 2020, this man served as chief judge of the D.C. circuit. This man prosecuted the perpetrators of the Oklahoma City bombing and rose to fame when a Republican Senate majority refused to consider his nomination for the Supreme Court. In his highest position, this man vowed to bring to justice those who stormed the U.S. Capitol on January 6th, 2021. For ten points, name this jurist who became U.S. Attorney General in March 2021.",
      "answer": "Merrick Garland"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Spanish Arch in Galway was partly destroyed by one of these events. Ammianus Marcellinus recorded one of these events which destroyed Alexandria in a \"day of horror.\" \"Meteo\" types of these events often hit Britain, and a confirmed example of these events in Scotland was caused by the Storegga slide. 230 thousand people died in a 2004 Boxing Day event of this type in the Indian Ocean. Thucydides correctly postulated that oceanic earthquakes caused, for ten points, what deadly tidal waves?",
      "answer": [
        "Tsunamis",
        "Meteotsunamis",
        "Tidal Waves before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A secret society that formed in this city originated from the Luojiao [[LWOH-JEOW]] Buddhist sect and was known as the Green Gang. A photograph titled Bloody Saturday depicts a crying baby among the ruins of one of this city's train stations. In a battle in this city, Lieutenant Oyama was killed at its Hongqiao [[HUNG-CHOW]] Airport. A 1937 battle in this city was referred to as “Stalingrad on the Yangtze.” For ten points, name this Chinese city occupied by Japan through much of World War Two.",
      "answer": "Shanghai 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict included a campaign to capture the town of Samosata. Robert Curthouse arrived to this conflict after Kilij Arslan was defeated at Nicaea. Bohemond of Taranto won at this campaign's Battle of Dorylaeum. Near the end of this conflict, Godfrey of Bouillon [[bwee-YOHN]] successfully fended off a Fatimid attack at Ascalon. This campaign was called for at the Council of Clermont by Pope Urban II with a cry of \"Deus Vult!\" For ten points, name this 11th century campaign in which Christians recaptured the Holy Land.",
      "answer": [
        "First Crusade",
        "Princes’ Crusade"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1855, this politician imported 33 camels and hired eight expert camel herders in order to create the experimental U.S. Camel Corps. During the Mexican-American War, while still a sitting U.S. Senator, this politician armed and outfitted the Mississippi Rifles. As Secretary of War under Franklin Pierce, this man promoted the Gadsden Purchase of southern Arizona from Mexico. Later, this man governed another country from Richmond. For ten points, name this politician who served as president of the Confederacy.",
      "answer": "Jefferson Davis 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A picture in Life magazine that came to symbolize this event depicted a wounded 12-year old named Joe Bass, Jr. This event was instigated by the arrest and beating of cab driver John William Smith. Along with a similar event in Detroit, this was the most devastating incident during the “long, hot summer.” During this event, the Jackson Street Bridge over the Passaic River was closed after a 6 p.m. curfew. For ten points, name these 1967 race riots which affected the most populous city in the “Garden State.”",
        "answer": "1967 Newark Race Riots"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This man was elected mayor of Newark in 2006 and held that office for seven years before resigning to take his seat as the first African-American U.S. senator from New Jersey.",
        "answer": "Cory Booker"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Diego Velázquez and Albrecht Dürer painted portraits of individuals with this condition, which supposedly forced one king to \"swallow everything whole.\" Charles II of Spain was called \"the Bewitched\" for this notable condition, among other health issues. This condition, whose medical name is \"mandibular prognathism,\" is often caused by inbreeding. For ten points, name this medical condition especially prevalent among members of its namesake royal house, also known as the \"Austrian lip.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Habsburg jaw",
          "Mandibular prognathism before mentioned",
          "Austrian lip before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The death of Charles II led to a diplomatic crisis over his lack of heirs, though the throne ultimately fell to this grandson of Louis XIV, who was forced to renounce the French crown.",
        "answer": [
          "Philip V of Spain",
          "Philip, Duke of Anjou"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After reciting a poem by Ziya Gökalp [[yoo-KALP]], this man was barred from public office for inciting religious hatred. This man sought to purge his government of secular personnel with help from Fethullah Gülen [[feh-TOO-lah goo-LEHN]]. This man founded his country's Justice and Development Party, or AKP, in 2001, and this man openly criticized his country’s “I Apologize” campaign, which aimed to formally acknowledge the Armenian genocide. For ten points, name this man who was elected president of Turkey in 2014.",
        "answer": "Recep Tayyip Erdoğan ] be very lenient on pronunciation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2020, Erdoğan controversially reclassified this museum as a mosque. This Byzantine cathedral had served as a museum since 1935.",
        "answer": "Hagia Sophia or Ayasofya 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The lyrics of this song include the line “Honour'd and blessed be the evergreen pine.\" The pointing of a cannon at the listener is compared to the playing of this song in the first verse of “Fortunate Son.” James Sanderson provided the music for this song, which took inspiration from The Lady of the Lake by Walter Scott. Famously played at the end of the War of 1812, Julia Tyler helped create the tradition of playing it at the arrival of her husband, John. For ten points, name this song, considered the personal anthem of the president of the United States.",
        "answer": [
          "Hail to the Chief",
          "Wreaths for the Chieftain"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Chester Alan Arthur did not like \"Hail to the Chief,\" asking this American \"March King\" to compose a new song, the \"Presidential Polonaise.\"",
        "answer": "John Philip Sousa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This entity was created after the fulfillment of a prophecy given by an oracle of Sabazios at Telmissus. In his Anabasis, Arrian chronicled a story involving this object, which was partly formed with an ox-driven cart belonging to its namesake. Found in Phrygia [[FRIH-jee-ah]], this item might have been destroyed with a linchpin or a sword. The conquest of lands as far as the Oxus throughout Asia is often attributed to the unraveling of this item. For ten points, Alexander the Great’s conquests are legendarily attributed to his untangling of what object?",
        "answer": "Gordian Knot"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander travelled to Siwa after conquering Egypt to determine his divine patronage. The oracle there declared him the \"son of [this god],\" equated with Zeus by the Greeks and fused with Ra by the Egyptians.",
        "answer": [
          "Amun",
          "Amon",
          "Amen",
          "Hammon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Ashin Wirathu supported Thein Sein's [[THANE-SANES]] plan to send these people to another country. A plan to relocate these people to Bhasan Char island by the Bangladeshi government was met with fierce opposition. These people are inhabitants of the former state of Arakan, now known as Rakhine state. The genocide and persecution of these people has been denied by their country's government, including Aung San Suu Kyi [[owng-sahn-soo-CHEE]]. For ten points, name this Muslim minority ethnic group persecuted by the government of Myanmar.",
        "answer": "Rohingya people"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This South African Anglican theologian and Nobel Peace Prize laureate compared the persecution of the Rohingya people to Apartheid.",
        "answer": "Bishop Desmond Tutu 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This force aided a resistance group by executing Operation Jericho in Amiens [[ah- MYANH]]. Operation Chastise was a campaign conducted by this group which involved a weapon invented by Barney Wallis which “bounced” to several targeted dams. In reference to this group, Winston Churchill once said, “Never was so much owed by so many to so few.” For ten points, name this military group which battled the Luftwaffe [[LOOFT-vah-fuh]] in the skies above Europe.",
        "answer": [
          "Royal Air Force",
          "RAF"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Britain began as an attempt by the Luftwaffe to gain air superiority so the German army could perform this operation, the planned invasion of Great Britain.",
        "answer": "Operation Sea Lion or Unternehmen Seelöwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Crownstones mark every fifth mile of this feature, which cuts across the Allegheny Mountains. This demarcation forms the northern and western boundaries of a region known as “The Wedge.\" This feature was originally surveyed to resolve a land dispute between Lord Baltimore and a descendant of William Penn. For ten points, name this demarcation which once marked the informal boundary between the Northern free states and Southern slave states in the U.S.",
        "answer": [
          "The Mason-Dixon Line",
          "Mason and Dixon Line",
          "Mason's and Dixon'sLine"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Just prior to his assassination, this president opened a new section of Interstate 95 along the Mason-Dixon line in one of his last public appearances.",
        "answer": "John Fitzgerald \"Jack\" Kennedy or JFK"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "First Ladies",
      "prompt": "Name the First Lady who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Assisted Thomas Jefferson before serving in the official role for the next president, her husband.",
          "answer": "Dolley Madison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was first to be the wife of one president and mother of another.",
          "answer": "Abigail Adams"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a glamorous socialite and author, and is a part of the \"Camelot Era.\"",
          "answer": "Jacqueline Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Started a Foundation for Family Literacy in 1989.",
          "answer": "Barbara Bush"
        },
        {
          "question": "Championed the contemporary Equal Rights Amendment and founded a substance abuse clinic.",
          "answer": "Betty Ford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has co-led the annual Habitat for Humanity Work Project since 1984.",
          "answer": "Rosalynn Carter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called \"Lemonade Lucy\" because of her support of the temperance movement.",
          "answer": "Lucy Webb Hayes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the niece of the widowed Andrew Jackson but butted heads with him during the Petticoat Affair.",
          "answer": "Emily Donelson 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Modern Welsh History",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital of Wales which was damaged in the Blitz during World War Two.",
          "answer": [
            "Cardiff",
            "Caerdydd"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Eldest son of Queen Elizabeth II, the longest-serving Prince of Wales.",
          "answer": "Charles, Prince of Wales"
        },
        {
          "question": "Welsh prime minister who was one of the \"big four\" at the Versailles peace negotiations.",
          "answer": "David Lloyd George"
        },
        {
          "question": "Author of Under Milk Wood who scripted wartime documentary series for BBC.",
          "answer": "Dylan Thomas"
        },
        {
          "question": "City nicknamed \"Copperopolis” which was bombed by the Luftwaffe in February, 1941.",
          "answer": [
            "City and County of Swansea",
            "Abertawe"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1966 collapse of a coal pile in a Welsh village that killed 116 children and 28 adults.",
          "answer": "Aberfan disaster"
        },
        {
          "question": "First parliamentary leader of the Labour Party who represented a town in South Wales.",
          "answer": "James Keir Hardie"
        },
        {
          "question": "Welsh Labour Party leader who names an ideology influenced by Marxism that opposed Gaitskellism.",
          "answer": "Aneurin \"Nye\" Bevan 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "First Nations",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Confederacy that fought the French-Canadians in the Beaver Wars.",
          "answer": [
            "Iroquois Confederacy",
            "Iroquois League",
            "the Six Nationss",
            "the Five Nations",
            "Haudenosaunee"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cultural monuments commonly carved from western red cedar in the Pacific Northwest.",
          "answer": "Totem poles"
        },
        {
          "question": "Arctic people group considered distinct from the First Nations and the Métis [[may- TEE]].",
          "answer": [
            "Inuit",
            "Inuuk"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former Confederacy that shares its name with one of the Great Lakes.",
          "answer": [
            "Huron or Wyandot",
            "or Wendat"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "British-allied tribe led by Joseph Brant during the American Revolution.",
          "answer": [
            "Mohawks or Kanienʼkehá꞉ka",
            "or Keepers of the Eastern Door"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "First Nation whose sub-groups include Plains, Woods, Swampy, and Moose.",
          "answer": [
            "Cree",
            "Néhinaw",
            "Néhiyaw"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Chief exonerated 133 years after his death by Justin Trudeau.",
          "answer": [
            "Poundmaker",
            "Pîhtokahanapiwiyin"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Deadly 1990 land dispute in Quebec between the government and the People of the Longhouse.",
          "answer": "Oka Crisis or Crise d'Oka 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) These people were led by Nicolas Durand de Villegaignon [[vih-leh-gah- NYOHN]] to the colony of Antarctique [[ant-ark-TEEK]] in modern day Brazil. John Everett Millais [[mee-LAY]] depicted a youth pulling off a white band wrapped around his arm in a painting titled for one of these people set during the St. (20 pts)",
        "Bartholomew's Day massacre. Louis XIV revoked many of Cardinal Richelieu's protections for these people after passing the Edict of (10 pts)",
        "Fontainebleau. The Edict of Nantes [[NAHNT]] granted rights to, for ten points, what group of French Calvinists?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Huguenots",
        "French Protestants",
        "French Calvinists before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Gouverneur Morris opposed the passage of this document, doubting the usefulness of direct taxes. This measure did not apply to a group \"bound to service for a term of years\" and \"[excludes] (20 pts)",
        "Indians not taxed.\" Some historians believe that Thomas Jefferson’s victory in the election of 1800 and the passage of the (10 pts)",
        "Missouri Compromise likely occurred due to this agreement. For ten points, name this compromise which counted slaves as a certain fraction of a person for purposes of representation."
      ],
      "answer": "Three-fifths Compromise or Article 1, Section 2, Clause 3 of the U.S. Constitution"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist was promoted to Accountant General after serving as a currency officer in Burma. This man was the first person of Asian descent to win a Nobel Prize, and this man was inspired by a trip along the Mediterranean to investigate the (20 pts)",
        "blue color of the sea. This man once destroyed a Bharat Ratna medallion given to him by Prime Minister Nehru in protest of the latter’s policies. This man's best known discovery involved the behavior of (10 pts)",
        "photons passing through transparent material. For ten points, name this Indian physicist who names a type of scattering."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "C.V. Raman or Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman",
        "Raman scattering",
        "Raman effect"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Carole Pateman argued that this concept shifted the means by which men had dominated women. Pierre-Joseph Proudhon created an individualistic form of this concept. A book named for this concept posits that the sovereign should act only to benefit the (20 pts)",
        "\"general will.\" The line \"Man is born free, yet everywhere is in chains\" opens a work titled for this concept by (10 pts)",
        "Jean-Jacques Rousseau. For ten points, name this concept in which people surrender some freedoms in exchange for the protection of their rights by the state."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Social Contract",
        "On the Social Contract",
        "or, Principles of Political Right",
        "Du contrat social",
        "ou Principes du droit politique 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The USCBB raised concerns that this company utilized the cell line of a fetus aborted in 1985 for one effort. This company, based out of New Brunswick, New Jersey, partnered with Janssen (20 pts)",
        "Pharmaceuticals in 1961. A major effort by this company has been hampered by reports of extremely rare blood (10 pts)",
        "clots. This company's COVID-19 vaccine is intended to require only one shot, unlike Moderna and Pfizer. For ten points, name this American pharmaceutical company, also known for Band- Aids, Tylenol, and baby products."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Johnson & Johnson or J&J",
        "Janssen Pharmaceuticals before \"Brunswick\""
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a terminus for trade between this empire and Russia, the city of Friedrichstadt was founded by Adam Olearius. Lala Mustafa Pasha fought this empire's ruler Mohammad Khodabanda. Red-headed holy warriors called the (20 pts)",
        "Qizilbash [[kih-zeel-BAHSH]] helped found this empire. Humayun the Mughal sought refuge from this empire's ruler Tahmasp. This empire's longest-serving ruler, (10 pts)",
        "Abbas the Great, negotiated the Treaty of Amasya with Suleiman the Magnificent. For ten points, name this gunpowder empire which ruled Persia from 1501 to 1736."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Safavid Empire",
        "Safavid Dynasty",
        "Safavid Iran",
        "Safavid Persia",
        "Safavids"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler forced Prince Mikhail Golitsyn to sleep in an ice castle on a cold night, and this ruler founded the Cadet Corps and Secret Office of Investigation. Married to Frederick William, Duke of (20 pts)",
        "Courland, this empress had an affair with Ernst Johann von Biron, influencing her to favor Baltic Germans in (10 pts)",
        "St. Petersburg. This ruler's reign is traditionally considered a \"dark era\" by Russian historians. For ten points, name this empress of Russia, who succeeded the grandson of her uncle, Peter the Great."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Anna of Russia",
        "Anna Ioannovna",
        "Anne in place of Anna"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As a result of this policy, the KKE was defeated in a civil war in one country. This policy was initiated partially in response to George F. Kennan's \"Long Telegram,\" which introduced the word (20 pts)",
        "\"containment\" into foreign policy. Developed in response to the Turkish Straits Crisis and the Greek Civil War, this policy was enacted to avoid a (10 pts)",
        "\"Domino Effect.\" Leading to the founding of NATO, for ten points, what U.S. policy aimed to contain Soviet expansion by aiding foreign countries?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Truman Doctrine",
        "Containment before mentioned 2020-21 National History Bowl - 2021-04-24 Round 7"
      ]
    }
  ]
}